Beth: While not all children with
autism have speech and language
delays, autism frequently causes
social communication challenges and
therefore delays in social development.
Children with autism may have a harder
time using or understanding non-verbal
communication such as pointing and
smiling and conversation tends to
come across with little animation
or inflection in their speech.
Joe: Individuals with High
functioning Autism can use language
to communicate with other people.
But their core communication problems,
often make it impossible for them
to learn language in the normal
way, which relies heavily on social
context, and non-verbal communications.
They may be more motivated by
their own interests rather than
by social responses and may rarely
or never imitate others' actions.
Beth: Some individuals with autism use
language intellectually and are highly
literal in how they use and understand
it, in contrast to the figurative
way most other people use language.
They find it difficult to understand
and rarely use sarcasm and irony and
other forms of communication where one
thing is said while another is meant.
Joe: Because of their difficulty
understanding body language and
nonverbal communication they often
cannot pick up on hints and clues that
people drop to indicate interest or
disinterest in what is being discussed
or an activity that is happening.
Beth: People with the most severe cases of
autism spectrum disorder typically require
very substantial support from others.
They may be completely isolated.
They may not use language at all,
or they may even be very limited
in their ability to communicate.